# Brian H. Rutledge

Software Solutions Arlington, MA 617-955-7782 <u>brian@bhrutledge.com</u> <u>http://linkedin.com/in/bhrutledge</u> <u>http://github.com/bhrutledge</u>

I have been writing and using software to solve problems for over 12 years. I enjoy studying software systems and explaining how they work.

I was an embedded software engineer for three years, then left the industry in 2005 to pursue peopleoriented work. I was fortunate to find it at a large bike shop, where I enjoyed the flow of a variety roles, from selling bikes to administering software, all focused on connecting customers with cycling. In my free time, I have expanded my software development skills by building responsive websites back-to-front. In 2014, I made the switch to professional web development, with a focus on exercising my skills with likeminded people working to speed the adoption of renewable energy.

### Skills

Adapting, Assimilating, Coding, Communicating, Debugging, Editing, Explaining, Programming, Researching, Teaching, Testing, Troubleshooting. **Software Development:** Python, SQL, Git, Travis, Linux/Unix, Test-Driven Development, Virtual Machines. **Web Development:** Django, Flask, Selenium, HTML, CSS, Markdown, JavaScript, jQuery, Apache, Responsive Design, Typography, Photography.

## **Experience**

#### **Web Developer**

2014-Present

EnergySage, Inc. Cambridge, MA

Back-end development on a Diango-based online marketplace for solar panel installation

#### **Full Stack Web Developer**

Freelance

2006-Present

- Built a <u>Flask & jQuery web application</u> to transform tab-delimited files into searchable and sortable tables, enabling a small retailer to quickly analyze sales reports
- Built my band's website using custom Django applications
- Built my personal website with the Pelican Python framework
- Built a musician's website with the Perch PHP framework
- Developed a <u>PHP framework</u> for quickly building <u>brochure websites</u>
- Built single-page <u>brochure websites</u> with responsive layouts
- Deployed websites to Linux shared hosting services, installing software as needed
- Managed my band's mailing list using GNU Mailman, then migrated to MailChimp to improve usability

#### **IT Operations Manager**

2007-2014

Belmont Wheelworks
Belmont, MA

- Built and managed the <u>business website</u> using the SmartEtailing CMS, and developed a custom frontend with CSS and JavaScript
- Wrote Python scripts to synchronize the store's inventory to the website catalog, resulting in increased customer inquiries and foot traffic
- Wrote SQL queries and Python scripts to generate custom reports of customers and inventory, streamlining tasks such as mailing list generation and barcode management
- Developed a physical count procedure and programmed a handheld data collector to improve inventory accuracy
- Built a Squarespace website for the in-house frame builder
- Configured and managed the MindBody web application to replace a paper binder for appointment booking
- Configured and managed Google Apps for email, calendars, and documents
- Maintained a Google Site for the company intranet, documenting numerous procedures and policies, and enabling easy viewing of schedules and calendars
- Managed a major upgrade of the CounterPoint retail management software
- Established and managed the relationship with an IT consulting firm to ensure timely and competent network management for all locations
- Provided IT vendors with on-site troubleshooting, hardware installation, and new project scopes, resulting in expedited solutions to problems and fewer billable support hours
- Provided staff training and support for all software systems
- Designed web and print forms for collecting customer questions and information

### Bicycle Fitter, Buyer, Salesperson

2006-2014

- Installed, replaced, and adjusted bicycle components and instructed clients on pedal technique and posture, resulting in a more comfortable, efficient, and safe experience
- Completed bicycle fitting certification programs from SBCU, SICI, and Retül
- Managed customer relationships by email, phone, and appointment
- · Ordered and stocked electronics, saddles, nutrition, and media
- Trained staff and customers on electronics

#### **Buyer, Sandwich Maker, Barista**

2005-2006

Darwin's Ltd. Cambridge, MA

- Ordered and stocked raw ingredients and paper goods
- Prepared and served beverages and sandwiches

#### **Software Engineer**

2001-2005

Applied Innovation Inc. Dublin, OH

- Assumed sole development responsibility for a troubled network device, turning it into a major source of income
- Designed, developed, and documented features for network devices using 68k Assembly, C, C++, Java, and Python
- Designed and developed a Perl web application for automated regression testing of network devices
- Completed software releases as sole developer and as part of a team
- Diagnosed and addressed field issues in conjunction with customer service

# **System Operations Center Operator, Lab Consultant** 2000-2002

The Ohio State University Columbus, OH

- Responded to help requests in a Unix and Windows environment
- Designed and developed a graphic FAQ editor in Java
- Provided programming and Unix assistance to students in labs of 50-100 computers

#### Grader

1999-2000

- Graded papers for an introductory software development course in C++
- Provided guidance for 35-40 students during and outside of class

## Education

# **Bachelor of Science, Computer & Information Science** 2002

The Ohio State University Columbus, OH

Graduated Cum Laude with Honors in the Liberal Arts, 3.640 GPA